In this series, I'll talk about middleweight bicycles.
A lot of people confuse middleweight bicycles with balloon tire bicycles.
They use a generic term, cruiser, which could apply to a balloon tire bicycle, or a middleweight bicycle, but I'll show you the difference between the two, and what makes it a cruiser, and not a cruiser.
I'll talk about how to identify a true middleweight bicycle, from a reproduction bicycle.
I'll talk about the design influences.
The balloon tire bikes were designed like streamlined, art deco motorcycles.
The middleweight bicycles have more of a space age look to them.
The rear racks will be more pointed.
The headlights will be integrated.
Usually, you have double headlights.
The tanks are slimmer.
The frames have thinner tubes, and are much lighter, and the gearing on the bicycle is different, than on a balloon tire bicycle.
The front chain ring on these cycles is larger.
I'll show you how to look at that, and how you determine the general gear ratio of these cycles.
I'll show you what manufacturers were successful, and what items were not successful.